Guide to the Alan Pryce-Jones Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alan Pryce-Jones papers
1857-2000
1915-1990
GEN MSS 513
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
33.2
(72 boxes)
The Alan Pryce-Jones papers consist of correspondence, manuscripts and printed versions of writings, family papers, diaries, financial papers, scrapbooks, photographs and other personal papers. Series I., Correspondence, includes letters from literary colleagues and acquaintances, family, and friends. It documents Pryce-Jones's career as a writer and editor, including many substantive letters from other writers and editors about their work. It also documents his family history, family relationships, and his social life as a member of the English and European aristocracy and, later in life, of American high society. Major correspondents, beyond Pryce-Jones's immediate family, include the Duchess of Buccleuch and Queensberry and Sir John Betjeman, among many others. Some third-party correspondence is also present. Series II., Writings, contains drafts and printed versions of Pryce-Jones's writings in many genres from throughout his long career. In addition to a large quantity of essays and reviews of literature, music, and theatre, the series includes juvenilia, novels, stories, memoirs, travel books, biographies, translations, poetry, plays, and libretti. Series III., Photographs, contains a photograph album of childhood portraits, as well as snapshots and formal portraits of Pryce-Jones from childhood through his eighties. The series also contains images of his family and friends, including two groups of photos taken at the homes of W. Somerset Maugham and Cyril Connolly. Series IV., Personal Papers, includes diaries, financial papers, family papers, and a few papers relating to Pryce-Jones's military work in MI14 during World War II and his brief political candidacy in 1939. It also includes files relating to renovation and restoration of Pryce-Jones's homes, particularly in Newport, and other personal papers such as address books and travel itineraries.
Other Storage Formats: 1 broadside folder, cold storage
Pryce-Jones, Alan, 1908-2000
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bertram Rota Ltd. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1989, and Gifts of Alan Pryce-Jones, 1991-98.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 69-71, and items in cold storage: Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
ALAN PRYCE-JONES
Heralded as one of the most promising writers of his generation in the early 1930s, Alan Pryce-Jones made his mark on twentieth century literature as an editor and critic, most significantly as editor of the Times Literary Supplement in the 1950s. A member of both the social and the intellectual elite in Britain, Europe and America, he lived his life on a large scale, finding success in what pleased him most: literature, music, travel, and society.
Alan Payan Pryce-Jones was born in London on November 18, 1908. He was the first child of Henry Morris Pryce-Jones, a colonel in the Army's Coldstream Guards and son of Welsh textile manufacturer Sir Pryce Pryce-Jones, and Vere Dawnay Pryce-Jones, granddaughter of Charles Grey, Private Secretary to Queen Victoria. His only sibling, Adrian, was born in 1919. The family lived near Buckingham Palace in Pryce-Jones's childhood, moving to a residence in Windsor Castle when his father joined the King's Body Guard in the 1920s. Pryce-Jones was close to his parents, and also to his maternal grandmother, Lady Victoria Dawnay, sister of the fourth Earl Grey. With her, he was a frequent guest throughout his early life in the great houses and castles of numerous titled relations.
He was educated at Eton, where he displayed a strong interest in and talent for music and literature, winning the school's Hervey prize for English Literature three years in a row. By his own account a precocious talent, he was encouraged by his parents and by critics to whom they sent his writings. After Eton he spent several months at Montbazon, in Touraine, France, before entering Magdalen College, Oxford, in 1927. Apparently without even a pretense of study, he enjoyed a busy social life at Oxford with new friends such as John Betjeman, and was sent down before the end of his second term.
Despite this unpromising exit from academia, in 1928 Pryce-Jones was offered an unpaid position as assistant editor of The London Mercury. He remained there, under editor J. C. Squire, until 1932, building a network of literary connections and earning money by writing for other publications.
During this period Pryce-Jones also began to travel extensively with a friend of the family, Robert Pratt-Barlow. Pratt-Barlow introduced him to Sicily, the Middle East and Eastern Europe in 1930. The two travelled to South America in 1931, and to Africa in 1932. From these experiences came Pryce-Jones's first two books, The Spring Journey (1931), an account of his travels in the Middle East, and People in the South (1932), a collection of stories set in South America. Both were very well received, and they, along with his Beethoven (1932) and Little Innocents (1932), earned Pryce-Jones literary celebrity by the age of twenty-four.
After leaving the Mercury, Pryce-Jones wrote for the illustrated paper The Sketch, among other publications. He based himself in London, but continued to travel often. In December 1932 he became engaged to Joan Eyres-Monsell, the sister of an Eton friend, but the disapproval of her parents gradually put an end to this attachment. Not long afterwards, while spending the winter of 1933-34 in Vienna, Pryce-Jones met Baroness Thérèse Fould-Springer.
Called "Poppy" by those close to her, Thérèse Fould-Springer was the daughter of Baroness Mary ("Mitzi") Springer (later Mrs. Frank Wooster) and the late Baron Eugène Fould, and heir, with her three siblings, to a vast inheritence including estates in France, Austria, Hungary and Czechoslovakia. With the enthusiastic approval of her mother and stepfather, Thérèse and Alan Pryce-Jones were engaged in September of 1934, and married on December 28 at Royaumont, one of the family's homes near Paris.
After their wedding, the couple lived in the Fould-Springers' house in Meidling, outside Vienna. Their only child, David, was born there on February 15, 1936. That same year, Pryce-Jones's Private Opinion: a Commonplace Book was published. Despite a comfortable life in Austria, by 1937 Thérèse's Jewish background made it unwise to remain there, and they moved to England at the end of that year.
Back in England, Pryce-Jones finished his first novel, Pink Danube, which was published in 1939 under the pseudonym Arthur Pumphrey. He ran as the Liberal Party's candidate for Louth, in Lincolnshire, in 1939, but his political career was cut short by the outbreak of the Second World War. He began the war as a captain in the 4th Hussars, and served briefly in France before transferring to MI14 in 1940. As an intelligence officer, he remained in London until 1945, although his family moved to Tonbridge, Kent after their London home was damaged by bombs in 1942. Following final assignments in Italy and Vienna, Lieutenant-Colonel Pryce-Jones was discharged in 1946.
After the war, Pryce-Jones joined the staff of the Times Literary Supplement. He became assistant editor in 1947, and was chosen to succeed Stanley Morrison as editor in 1948. He remained in this post for eleven years, earning the highest praise from his contemporaries. He is credited with significantly revitalizing the publication--and with it English literary culture--by broadening its scope to include work by European and American writers, and by raising the quality of the reviews.
Early in Pryce-Jones's tenure at the Times, his wife became seriously ill following a miscarriage. After several years of struggle against what was eventually diagnosed as cancer, Thérèse died in February 1953, in Paris. Pryce-Jones remained very close to her family for the rest of his life. He also maintained close ties with the Rothschilds, relations by marriage through Thérèse's younger sister Liliane, Baroness Elie de Rothschild.
Throughout the late 1940s and '50s, Pryce-Jones led a busy life, both professionally and personally. In addition to his work at the Times, he travelled throughout the world on lecture tours for the British Council, made frequent appearances on BBC radio and television, translated, among other works, Strauss's Der Rosenkavalier (1947), and wrote the libretto for Lennox Berkeley's opera Nelson (1954). He was a trustee of the National Portrait Gallery, the Old Vic Trust, and the Royal Literary Fund, among other such duties. He converted to Catholicism in 1950. Several years after his wife's death, he began to see a great deal of his distant cousin Mary ("Mollie"), Duchess of Buccleuch and Queensberry, who remained his close confidante until her death in 1993.
Pryce-Jones voluntarily stepped down as editor of the Times Literary Supplement in 1959, in order to pursue fresh challenges. He became theater critic for The Observer for a year, while its regular critic Kenneth Tynan was on leave in New York, and then accepted an offer to go to New York himself for a short time as an adviser to the Ford Foundation, in 1960. A widower for some years, with both parents now deceased and his son grown, Pryce-Jones had few responsibilities in England, and soon decided to stay in America permanently.
He did not remain with the Ford Foundation long, preferring to resume his own writing career. He collaborated on a musical version of Vanity Fair with Robin Miller and Julian Slade, which premiered in London in 1962. He became a literary critic for the New York Herald Tribune, and, after it folded, the World Journal Tribune and the Washington Post. He also had a column in Theatre Arts, and wrote for a wide range of other publications. Throughout the 1960s and '70s, he appeared frequently on BBC radio both as a reviewer and as a commentator on American life, and continued to lecture through the British Council and other agencies.
In 1963 Pryce-Jones purchased two small houses in Newport, Rhode Island, which he renovated extensively. A third house made possible extended visits by friends and family from abroad, and throughout the 1960s he divided his time between New York and Newport. In 1968, he married Mary Jean Kempner Thorne, a journalist and member of a prominent Galveston, Texas, family. A year later, she became ill while vacationing in Portugal and was rushed to the American Hospital in Paris, where she died, in September 1969, of aplastic anaemia. After her death, Pryce-Jones remained close to her mother and to his stepson, Daniel Thorne, Mary Jean's only child by her first marriage.
Pryce-Jones moved to Newport permanently in the 1970s. He spent part of each year abroad with family and friends, particularly with his son David and daughter-in-law Clarissa (Caccia), their three children, and the extended Fould-Springer family. He traveled frequently, most often with the Duchess of Buccleuch or Cecile de Rothschild, but also with Larry Hudson, his close companion in later years.
Pryce-Jones continued to write and review throughout the rest of his life, on a wide variety of subjects. In 1987 his memoir, The Bonus of Laughter was published in England. He died January 22, 2000, in Galveston, Texas.
For more information about Pryce-Jones's family connections, see the Appendix. See also his memoir, The Bonus of Laughter.
Scope and Contents
The Alan Pryce-Jones Papers consist of correspondence, diaries, manuscripts and printed versions of writings, photographs, scrapbooks, financial papers and other personal papers of the English writer, editor, and critic Alan Pryce-Jones. They span the years 1857-2000, with the bulk falling between about 1915 and 1990. The papers are organized into four series: Correspondence, Writings, Photographs, and Personal Papers. Groups of Oversize material and Restricted Fragile Papers are also present.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries: Alan Pryce-Jones Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence.
Alan Pryce-Jones Correspondence spans the years 1913-1996. Because there is no clear boundary between Pryce-Jones's literary work and personal life, or between his family and friends, his correspondence is arranged in a single alphabetical sequence. It documents his career as a writer and editor, as well as his relationships with immediate and extended family, close friends, and acquaintances.
Pryce-Jones's literary career is documented in correspondence with literary agents, publishers, and contributors to publications and single works he edited, as well as with collaborators and close friends who were also writers. Correspondence from Evan Morgan, for instance, is accompanied by heavily edited copies of Pryce-Jones's poems.
His work with the Times Literary Supplement is documented in one folder of correspondence from other editors and staff members at the Times itself; this includes his work as editor as well as his ongoing relationship with the paper as a contributor after 1959. His work as editor is also documented to a limited extent in more personal correspondence from other editors, and more fully in his correspondence from the many reviewers he worked with and cultivated, and from writers whose work was reviewed.
Pryce-Jones's correspondence also documents his childhood and school experiences, immediate and extended family relationships, and friendships throughout his life with a wide range of well-known figures in England, Europe, and America. Correspondence with his immediate family contains the only substantial quantity of outgoing letters from Pryce-Jones in the collection. These include letters to his parents, his grandmother Victoria Dawnay, and his brother Adrian; in the case of his parents, the bulk of the correspondence is outgoing. Generally these letters to his parents contain detailed accounts of Pryce-Jones's daily life and of those around him, and document his experiences at Eton and Oxford, visits to extended family, his courtship of Thérèse Fould-Springer, his early married life, and other aspects of his life up to the beginning of World War II. (Outgoing letters, here and in the very few other files in which they occur, are interfiled with incoming correspondence.)
In addition to the twenty-five folders of correspondence with his parents, other correspondence from immediate family includes nine folders of letters from Pryce-Jones's first wife, Thérèse, which document their engagement, their life together, and her last illness. Letters from their son David are chiefly from the period after Pryce-Jones moved to America, and to a great extent document David's own career as a writer, in addition to family matters.
The largest volume of correspondence in the collection (thirty-eight folders) is from Mary ("Mollie"), Duchess of Buccleuch and Queensberry, spanning the years 1954-1992. These letters document the close relationship that she and Pryce-Jones shared for forty years. They contain much information about her family, particularly her children and grandchildren, and about mutual friends and relations in the British aristocracy. She sometimes wrote more than once a day and frequently enclosed letters to her from mutual friends and acquaintances. A number of her letters to Pryce-Jones, particularly concentrated in 1956-57, were unopened when the papers were acquired by the Library. These letters have been opened by Library staff, and placed in enclosures indicating this. (A few unopened letters found elsewhere in the series were treated in the same manner.)
Many other close friendships over the course of Pryce-Jones's long life are documented by comparatively fewer, yet not insignificant numbers of letters from each correspondent. Among his more frequent correspondents at various points in his life were David Astor, John Betjeman, Roger de Candolle, Harry and Rosemary D'Avigdor-Goldsmid, Billa Harrod, Patrick Kinross, Mary Loder, Harold Nicolson, Vere and Honor Pilkington, Robert Pratt-Barlow, Shirley and LeClare Ratteree, the Sitwells, Stephen Spender, and James Stern, to mention only a few. He also maintained regular correspondence with the extended Fould-Springer family: there are substantial files of letters from his mother-in-law Mary Wooster; sisters-in-law Liliane de Rothschild and Hélène Propper de Callejon; brother-in-law Baron Max Fould-Springer; their spouses and children; and from Cecile and Clarice de Rothschild.
Pryce-Jones was long established within the most prominent twentieth- century literary and social circles, and he was well connected in the classical music world as well. Consequently, his correspondence also includes single or small quantities of letters from a considerable number of well-known figures. In addition to writers and intellectuals of high standing on both sides of the Atlantic, British and European royalty and aristocracy are well represented, as is American high society. His correspondents reflect the broad spectrum of his social and professional experience, ranging from George Bernard Shaw to Eudora Welty; from Winston Churchill to Elsa Maxwell; from Princess Margaret to Lincoln Kirstein; and including nearly everyone imaginable in between.
Several folders of letters from unidentified correspondents, or from those identified only by first name, are present at the end of the subseries.
(A small amount of correspondence from banks, financial advisors, legal representatives, and insurance agents, as well as from contractors and other tradespeople, can be found in Series IV. This body of correspondence was present within a distinct group of files documenting Pryce-Jones's financial affairs; as such, it was kept among those files rather than interfiled with the main correspondence series. There is, therefore, some overlap between Series I and Series IV, as a small amount of correspondence from financial and legal representatives and tradespeople can be found throughout Series I, chiefly but not exclusively in the "letter general" files.)
The second subseries, Third Party Correspondence, spans the years 1876 to 1994, and contains letters to and from members of Pryce-Jones's family, his friends, and the editors who preceded him at The London Mercury and the Times Literary Supplement. It is arranged alphabetically under headings for each recipient for whom multiple letters are present, with a final heading for Other Third Party Correspondence, which contains single letters to and from other parties. Correspondents include Pryce-Jones's parents Henry and Vere Pryce-Jones; his brother Adrian; his son David; his cousin Mary Loder; his first wife Thérèse Fould-Springer Pryce-Jones and her siblings; his mother-in-law Mary Wooster; his grandmother Lady Victoria Dawnay and her sisters Louisa, Countess of Antrim and Mary, Countess of Minto; his second wife Mary Jean Kempner; George Dix; Larry Hudson; Mary ("Mollie"), Duchess of Buccleuch and Queensberry; Sir John Collings Squire; and Stanley Morrison.
Letters to and from family members and close friends are largely personal, although many letters are from well-known figures such as Lord Kitchener or Noël Coward. Many of the letters to Pryce-Jones's parents favorably discuss his early writings. Correspondence to Squire and Morrison is chiefly from contributors to the Mercury and the Times Literary Supplement, respectively. These include, for example, Max Beerbohm, Lord Alfred Douglas, and Siegfried Sassoon, among others.
Series II, Writings is organized into twelve subseries: Books; Short Stories; Essays, Lectures and Radio Appearances; Reviews; Obituaries, Eulogies, and Tribute Speeches; Lyrics, Libretti and Plays; Poetry; Juvenilia; Translations and Edited Works; Scrapbooks; Notebooks; and Writings of Others. The series spans circa 1914 to 1996. Writings in all genres from the period before 1927 are filed in the Juvenilia subseries.
For many of the subseries, the Scrapbooks and Notebooks subseries should be considered addenda, as they contain additional material for each genre. The Scrapbooks, in particular, contain numerous printed versions of poetry, essays, stories, and reviews by Pryce-Jones, intermingled on the pages. They also contain the majority of reviews of Pryce-Jones's writings. Because of the quantity of material in the scrapbooks, cross references have not been created from the other subseries.
Pryce-Jones used several pseudonyms in his career. A few letters in Series I addressed to "Marigold" suggest that he may have written under that name in the 1930s, although no writings signed "Marigold" appear in this series. Arthur Pumphrey, the pseudonym under which he published Pink Danube in 1939, appears also as the byline for some of the shorter works later in his career. He used the pseudonym George Cloyne beginning in the late 1950s and chiefly during his tenure at the Ford Foundation, which forbade its advisors to publish their own writings.
The first subseries, Books, spans 1932-1969 and is organized under two headings: Fiction and Non-Fiction. Material under Fiction includes the holograph draft and related material for Pryce-Jones's 1932 collection of stories, People in the South (published in the U.S. under the title Hot Places ); the holograph manuscript and some related material for Pink Danube; and a draft titled Seven Against Thebes. Material under Non-Fiction includes drafts, reviews, and other related material for Pryce-Jones's travel book The Spring Journey (1932), his biography of Beethoven (1932), his memoir The Bonus of Laughter (1987), and Private Opinion: A Commonplace Book (1936). It also includes contracts for a few other works for which no drafts are present. (As with works in other subseries, many reviews of Pryce-Jones's books can also be found in the Scrapbooks.)
Short Stories, the second subseries, contains drafts and printed versions of individual short stories. It is arranged alphabetically by title, with untitled drafts and fragments at the end of the sequence, and includes both drafts and printed versions. The stories are largely undated, but the date span is approximately 1927 through 1977. (Additional short stories can be found in the Scrapbooks, particularly in the scrapbook containing Pryce-Jones's writings published in The Sketch in the early 1930s (Box 66, folder 2430).)
The third subseries, Essays, Lectures and Radio Appearances, spans approximately 1929 to 1974. It contains a large volume of individual essays, lectures, and radio scripts in both draft and printed form. Because it is often difficult to discern for which forum a particular draft was intended, the drafts have been listed in a single alphabetical sequence, by title; two notebooks of holograph drafts are filed at the end of the alphabetical sequence, followed by Untitled Drafts and Fragments, Notes, and Related Material.
Many of the pieces in this subseries document BBC appearances, including a long series called "Month in New York," a commentary on current events in New York City, which aired between 1967 and 1972. The majority of the lectures identifiable as such are variations on the theme of twentieth century literature; another common theme is the experience of moving to America from England. Other pieces, including many essays, are critical studies of or introductions to works by individual writers; some are commentary on literature, society, and occaisionally politics, including a number of pieces for the column "Viewpoint" in the Times. Also present are transcripts of on-air conversations and interviews, and lighter essays which appeared in such publications as Mademoiselle or House and Garden.